24 hours for these competitors 32 divers
set out in hope at 7 o'clock last night
now we're down to the best 12 after the
Smalling semi-final reduced the number
down from 18 with defending champion
Matthew Mitchum without doubt the
big-name to miss out on tonight's final
when he finished an agonizing 13th
another packed house here in the Aquatic
Centre as they're introduced to the
finalists here
the majority of course will be noisily
rooting for the British home favorite
the poster boy for these London 2012
games who finished 4th in the semis with
his confidence and his performance
building steadily terrific mood all over
Olympic Park this evening as two amazing
week starts to reach its conclusion get
ready to hear those home supporters here
is Tom Daley
it's been a great games for Great
Britain that this young man just 18
years of age carries so many hopes on
his young shoulders he studies fan club
out in force tonight
well will he be inhibited or will he be
inspired David Boudia the American next
to him enjoying the occasion and
reveling in the atmosphere that's great
to see
but those supporters will know that it's
the Chinese duo have lent you here and
Cubo next to him we've been setting the
standards right from the off as they
chase their country's seventh diving
gold medal of the games his chuubo
leading after the semi finals and the
favorite for gold the six for those 12
finalists the Olympic Games is a new
experience unlike for Steve for
billiards sitting next to me Steve
you've been studying the scores over the
two rounds so far I mean how much is the
standard just built as this competition
has progressed I think it's really
significant Roger that from the men in
the top 12 who have qualified for this
final the lowest dive score in the semi
was 72 in that from Riley McCormick and
even that score dates but with a low
tariff so the consistency has really
been building in the preliminaries we
saw dives in the 30s and even a couple
in the 20s the lifting consistency for
the second phase of the competition was
remarkable and and now what we're
looking for is consistency with high
quality and that's what we're seeing
from cheer and Lin and it's hard to see
them being displaced from the top two
positions
you wouldn't say right from from the off
that it's a battle for the bronze but I
think a few people might be thinking
there yes in diving you cannot afford to
make one mistake there's no three
attempts as there is in the high jump or
the long jump it's one strike and you're
out really judges being introduced
they've got the toughest job of the lot
in here as this standard builds in the
competition seven of them have to judge
the execution of each dive which is
force is pre announced and given a
specific degree of difficulty or tariff
you'll be able to follow this quite
simply when the captions after each
diver is put on your screen for you the
top two in the bottom two marks are
discounted and those three remaining
marks are then multiplied by that degree
of difficulty and the basic rule is that
the higher the degree of difficulty the
bigger the prize certainly with the
lower degree certificate ease you've got
to execute them near perfectly to make
sure you maintain the sort of points
tour you'll need to and it's very
interesting to see Steve as it goes
through the order they go in a wallet
two of them coming out playing their big
dives early on hoping to post a good
score and one or two others starting a
bit more conservatively and I just think
that's a matter of horses for courses he
if it's to to to put in a tough dive
early because you feel focused at the
beginning of competition do it then we
saw some divers struggle towards the end
of the preliminaries it was such a long
session that their legs were weary they
admitted as much and and three of the
top six I think had their worst dive as
their sixth well they've had a good
break in the middle of the day today
maybe of talked about the short
turnaround from last night to this
morning that they should be well rested
now and we're expecting them to perform
at their best and they'll hope to do
that it was a three hour session last
night to reduce the numbers from thirty
to a couple of hours in the pool this
morning they've had a good rest they
were finished around about midday so
I've had a good eight hours or so back
to the village arrests trying to get the
mind straight and then back here they've
been warming up of course and now it is
for real
six dives each Riley McCormick from
Canada will lead us off and for many of
these divers a place in the final was
their first aim and now it's all about
what they can produce on the day Wiley
opening up with a four with three and a
half somersault piked
who solid opening from him at at 72 we
talked about as being the lowest score
from the top 12 was his opening dive and
because it's got a load tariff even
these eighths can't get him much above
low to mid-70s
there we go seventy six point five four
points he's picked up there from the
semi-final the same guy right at the top
of the scale they will be hitting three
figures with the points total so you're
really looking to be in the 80s to low
90s to keep those medal chances going
next
Alexander Banda from the Ukraine in with
three and a half somersault three point
two tariffs here for the young Ukrainian
just 18 years of age
very nice just the smallest hinge at the
hips seventy eight point four from the
semi-final for this dive to see how
vertical he enters the water very close
to perfect I'm not quite and he will be
penalized slightly for that were those
seven and a half coming in and only a 72
so it's not the start he wanted or
needed
bondar said he just wanted to get into
the final after the swelling's
performance and he did it but he must
make sure that it's not just satisfied
with that it and still continues to
really show what he can do at this level
third up is even Garcia from Mexico
silver medalist in the 10 meters synchro
already with Chioma Sanchez who missed
the boat unfortunately for him his
nickname is polo and I saw someone with
somehow paint on their backs and vamos
pollo let's go and go he does forward
four-and-a-half somersault three point
seven big opening dive from even Garcia
just a really difficult dive to control
the splash a little more than he might
have liked nice tight tuck position
spots the water the feet coming over
just a little about an eighty three
point two five to start for Navarro my
missus might miss his countrymen tonight
because they were chatting in the pool
afterwards and keeping each other going
a little bit but Jose Guerra 33 year old
Cuban diver
well he's showing again and again that
age is no barrier we've got a range of
17 up to 33 and he is the veteran in the
field and diving beautifully Cuba have
never won a diving medal he's generally
regarded as their greatest ever diver
made a handy start here
76.5 just a difficulty a little low but
eight and a half's you don't want less
than that when the tariff is average two
Germans in the final 12 this evening
Sasha Klein diving next is the older
more experienced of the two at 26 in
with three and a half somersault 3.2
tariffs now you were like sashes
Chancellor's don't you Roger there's an
outside chance for a middle I think he
said at the right age he's 26 he's he's
got eight European goals behind him he's
mature he's experienced to this level he
just needs to get it right so as a guide
seventy six point eight in the semi but
80 here so he's off and running
Nick McCrory is up next from the United
States bronze in the 10 metre synchro
already in his kit back in with three
and a half somersault tux position for
three point two degree of difficulty
what an entry very quiet into the water
and the u.s. cheer squad goes up seventy
six point eight in the semi very close
to the platform which always gives us a
nervous moment but he's got some nines
here McCrory and nines will be the three
scores that count he is flying out of
the blocks the Americans have had a good
competition so far a silver and two
bronze reviving those glory days when
they absolutely dominated in the pool at
86 his ten better than his score in the
semi Victor mini bio from Russia can he
match that sort of progress in would
three and a half somersault tucked three
point two
long hold at the top getting his
composure silence in the pool
well those legs folded over just a touch
he collapsed into the somersault under
the water to try and hold that position
again he's in tight to the platform
kicks out now and the legs over just a
little mini Bob's got a very ambitious
program with three dives of three six
and A three seven as well if he gets
them all he could be in the Middle's but
I have over stretched himself anyway
Eddie one six to start perfect match for
his semi final score now it's Martin
Wolfram from Germany his first Olympics
he's just 20 he admitted her to in the
preliminary competition he didn't do
that well because he was just so excited
gotta keep calm now with that arm stand
back double somersault two and a half
twists three point six big opening dive
very nice now this was the top-scoring
first round dive in the semi-final it
drew a 91 point eight for Wolfram
the cheer is not so much for his divers
for the man coming up next but it should
be for this dive because he has done
very well he's closing in on three
figures with this dive a sneaky look at
the scoreboard it's a 97 point to worry
that it's some statement but he's one of
only three divers to go with a high
tariff
first up dive and he's taken the reward
for the risk Tom Daly has been the
nation's young poster boy hero since
Beijing when he was the British team's
youngest member at 14 years of age back
two and a half somersault two and a half
twist three point six of the tariff Tom
Daly well the crowd wants it to be good
but he was short he never reached the
vertical position and the replays are
going to expose the error here they
wanted him to start with an emphatic
dive but there you see he wasn't at the
vertical nation expects and he almost
delivers so Tuffy built through his
program this morning but he cannot
afford well he can't afford many more
dives like that that's for certain
mid-seventies won't get the job done in
this company so 75 six but five dies now
some action on the deck here
a distraction alright we've got the
conversation coming now I'm wondering if
Tom Bailey
we can only guess from here Raja Ben Tom
Daly got out of the pool looking quite
concerned that something hadn't gone
right well there are flashes you see
people are asked not to have their flash
on for the cameras they've repeated that
at every session so far but haven't
heard it so far this evening now it
would be some controversy if they let
him dive again I can't remember that
happening in certainly hasn't happen in
these games and only the last couple of
World Championships I've been to now
he's come across to explain his point
[Music]
I think we've guessed it it's to do with
the flash photography and and I don't
think he's got really solid ground for a
read I've but was an official protest it
was go up he's going well wonder how the
rest of our field are gonna react to
this depending on what he does now I'm
sure there'll be another announcement
about the flash photography if that is
the basis for him
well that was clear enough and Tom Daly
has ladies get out of jail card may be
interesting to know how the rest of the
competitors react to that whether it's
sympathy for a fellow pro or they think
that he's got an unfair advantage it all
depends how he cashes in so Daly with
the read I've 75 six was what he got
first time around now the pressures on
him to get a better score than that but
we saw just from one angle that there
were at least half-a-dozen significant
flashes the first round of this
competition Oh much better effort well
if he is going to be handsomely rewarded
for putting in the protest Andry diving
and they pick a point on the ceiling or
somewhere in the pools to orientate
themselves around and that presumably is
at the heart of his his complaint the
flash catches his eye and he loses his
bearings in terms of spotting the
ceiling and it can totally put him off
well he has more than cashed in on the
opportunity to read up with a 91 eight
instead of a seventy five six his pulse
rate is up sky-high David Boudia had to
wait his turn twenty three-year-old from
Texas runs in the ten metre synchro arm
stand back double somersault two and a
half twists
very nice from the dire
I only just scraped into the semi-finals
if you weren't with us last night silver
medalist at World Championships almost
missed the second at stage of
competition but then walleston in third
place behind the two chinese divers and
he has started impressively very
impressively silver medalist from the
World Championships in Shanghai he's
probably got the the pedigree to justify
being among the medal contenders just
another reminder for the crown and I
can't help but think Roger there would
be plenty of people here who do not
speak English and the warning me might
may mean little to them fair point Lynn
that you a now the Chinese divers always
look totally in their own zone so their
concentration takes some shaking in
would three and a half somersault tucked
for the 21 year old the older of the two
Chinese divers
beautiful just what we expected
they know how to start a competition
they know how to win one and it's with
this quality he only had 81.6 for his
first dive in the semies but with the
nines and nine and a half's here it's
gonna be a very well three nine and a
half so what's gonna count we reject
that low nine rate start from him ninety
one two interestingly Lin this morning
after competition said he was desperate
for gold and really going to be trying
his best and Cubo said the Middle's not
so important I just want to do my best
mind you he knows that his best is the
best hue both a favorite in would three
and a half somersault three point to his
opening dive well there it is the
quality that we saw from Lin replicated
by chuubo don't expect him to be leading
after the first round because it's a
just a three point two tariff that he's
making the most of it oh the anyway you
attend just to whet your appetite for
what's ahead from this man
we keep coming back to that word
consistency but they they never seem to
let their standards slip and a ninety
one point two picked up a couple of more
points from his semi final effort with
that first dive so China very solid star
in fact though identical scores for Chu
Lin 91 - well there's the standings
after the first round
David budaya Marcin wolfram Tom Daly
then you a then Cuba Venrock Rory
there's yet another reminder from the
announcers about the flash photography
but again in this first round it's the
degree of difficulty which is the
deciding factor depending on which
tariffs dive these competitors open up
with we're all even itself out of course
second round of six while in McCormick
back two and a half somersault two and a
half twists three point six the tariff
for the TWiT year old Canadian
those leaks just folding over a little
on entry he made a rip-roaring start
with a fairly straight forward opening
dive to be in sixth position 86.4 member
he was the last qualifier into the final
but the feet just a little loss of leg
form there and then over rotating so not
a match in execution for his first dive
didn't make the final in Beijing he was
16th so this is progress for him in his
second Olympics all about the scores
though maybe six for steady eights
through the middle there
Alexander Banda from Ukraine forward
four and a half somersault three points
seven Terrace well well done control the
entry minimize the splash it wasn't
particularly convincing with the angle
of entry only just straightening out in
time but the judges will like that
impression of no splash it was a thinly
ten metre synchro competition with
Alexander Gorshkov us off
that's his highest Terrace dive as well
isn't it and an eighty eight point eight
make up a little bit of ground after his
first dive of 72 he van Garcia from
Mexico next to dive back three and a
half somersault three point three
tariffs here it's his first Olympic
Games just 18 years of age and away oh
he did a great job there very impressive
height off the platform really drove up
give himself time to get through the
somersaults and make it for an easy
entry I like this very tight tuck
position very good angle into the water
and not much of a splash there soon top
job he's one of the divers who came to
the World Cup event here in the Aquatic
Centre in February and was second in the
10 meters so well researched for his
trip Jose grown up from Cuba 33 year old
back through in a half somersault
just you see these more experienced
divers may not achieve that perfect
vertical position and yet they can still
find a way to minimize the splash and
here's a prime example of it you see he
was coming in at a little bit of an
angle didn't throw up too much water but
the judges will still have noticed that
he was not quite vertical it's his
fourth Olympic Games and he was a fifth
in Beijing so he's been making steady
progress in 88 - well done to the Cuban
now Sasha Klein from Germany not his
best opening dye forward for a half
somersault with that 3.7 taraf here well
by contrast with the previous dive he
had a good angle but but more splash now
with this dive in the semi scored a 90
point six five the splash might just be
a handbrake on his score here seven and
a half's coming in bronze medal in last
year's World Championships in Shanghai
so in 83 to five possessions second dive
it's given back a few points on the
semi-final score Nick McCrory in sixth
position after his opening dive this one
is an arm stand back double somersault
with one and a half twists 3.2 is the
tariff on how long the hold would be at
the top
it's a long hold and hear the gasp of
air the effort as he pushes away from
the platform when armed stands got to be
held long enough and steady enough to
convince the judges that you're
comfortable there and in control our
American has won this 10 metre platform
event since the great Greg Louganis in
88 in Seoul he's here in London with the
various media duties another great
school there for Macquarie he been after
more than 75 - but 7 and a half and 8
doesn't quite cut it in this company
Victor media buyer from Russia with a
forward four and a half somersault 3.7
already seen a few of these dives
completed or attempted
well that's one of the better ones and
when you're going for a three point
seven tariff it's a real opportunity to
move up the board and eighty six nine
five for this one in the semi for mini
buy of so much rotation there's so much
a spin speed a build build up hit the
water just over thirty people have tried
to calculate that it's knocking on
towards 60 mile an hour they're spinning
out but they take a bit of grasping
those figures ninety-two five these he's
picked up a few points by comparison
with these semi score net that's what
they'll be aiming to do just improve a
few points every dive not involved from
from Germany terrific opening dive in
with three and a half somersault just
the three point two tariffs here oh he's
done a beautiful job well while from
looks the man in early form with his
first two dives ninety seven to for his
first remember
he's obviously made terrific progress in
the last 12 months sir he didn't get
through qualification at the World
Championships last year his first big
event but he is flying now 86 for as he
had in the semi so wolfram making a
statement with his first two dives
demobilized the flash beef right to take
a photograph wouldn't he
Tom Daly after that dramatic read I've
now with an inward three and a half
somersault again a great dive
we won the national under-18 title when
he was only 10 and he's been a marked
man or boy ever since and it's nine-foot
for daily a 91 8 first dive and if
you're just joining us he got to retake
that first dive after a protest because
of flash photography in the room and he
picked up 15 points on his first effort
and an 86 for here he's on his way to
something maybe David Beckham's come to
watch him then no more lines about
diving and from football working
certainly not with Beck's
no that never happened David booty I
know the American in with three and a
half somersault again a really strong
opening dive three point two the tariff
[Applause]
Obadiah he was another to make a comment
about that short turnaround from prelims
to semi sit he only got six hours sleep
perform very well nonetheless as he is
doing in this final that's a a
spectacular second die from the dire he
was asked about nerves at this level of
competition and said if you ask all 12
divers whether they get nervous a
hundred percent will say yes
why wouldn't you it's not just a
competition it's what they're doing 10
meters up do put themselves in danger
each time then you a from China the 2008
Olympics synchro champion another
exquisite dive from Lin you a
ninety one point two threes first
starting to rack up the nines and nine
and a half's consistently now
so in control and the judges in absolute
unison with their assessment of 9.5 for
linear and a 90 405
he's the synchro specialist this is a
rare individual opportunity for Lin
unlike Chabot there's been the solostar
the 19 year old son of a factory worker
in Sichuan Province armed stand back
triple somersault three point five
perfect armed stand well that was
beautiful
this was a guy that he had a little bit
of a struggle with in the semi-final was
only the 13th ranked dive he made a
mistake and we were shocked to see it
because we're so used to perfection or
near to it from him but he has picked up
his game here with his second attempt at
it today
this competition is really going to be
tough
frightening ly impressive at the top and
the competition just below that 94.5 and
there he is he's moved to normal
transmission less risky and Roger is
number one both looks so calm during
competition the status quo chuubo Lin
you a David bouton Martin Wolfram having
a great first Olympics Tom Daley and
through to Alexander bond are bringing
out the rear at the moment but he's 12
out of 32 let's put it that way let's
give them the credit for reaching
through to this stage which for many of
them was their ambition to reach an
Olympic final such a fantastic occasion
and they will all feel privileged to be
diving alongside during competition to
the very best around
Riley McCormick can never won attend me
to medal we've had nine diving medals in
all he's coming in with three and a half
somersault to perform now this customary
little flicks into the opposition Court
or in this case into the water and he's
done a nice job there there's McCormick
they must have a trigger something that
say now is the moment a lot of if it
goes through those toes to get some
elevation
through the somersaults nice job here
good tight tuck excellent position into
the water
maybe one six steady I think most of us
would need a trigger to get up there and
the gun to go with it to jump off that
Timmy debord like they do should never
forget the sheer bravery of it while
we're admiring all the skill and all the
technique takes some nerve
now it's Alexander bond our arms stand
back double somersault two and a half
twist three point six tariffs here
very tidy on the entry now Banda is
about 25 points behind the leader so
he's to make a move it needs to come now
with dive number three pushing up and
out away from the platform
feet apart though I have to say probably
that the entry was the best part of the
dive but his leg form a little loose
ankles not together except for the end
maybe 2.84 bandha again we must point
out that we are privileged we see the
replays of the dives the judges of
course have just one shot at it to make
their judgment call or in Tom Daley's
case two shots at it this time hmm
that will be talked about especially if
he gets himself on the podium even
Garcia of Mexico have a 18 year old with
an inward four and a half somersault it
would dives frightening ly close to the
platform he's done a good job with it
too Mexican fans are happy he's got what
can only be described as a pretty gutsy
sheduled for himself as neat high
tariffs brave dives gambler
so the aches are gonna count the to
seven and a half will be rejected the
feet just drifting away from the ideal
line a ninety eight point four and
that's because of that four point one
tariff for tune favoring the brave there
with Yvonne Garcia the Barry brave Jose
get up from Cuba fifth in the ten metre
synchro event now with an inward three
and a half somersault 3.20
that's just something of a hold and
remember that was as good as it can be
done it's a low tariff so something in
the mid eighties is is a very good
reward
alright nines are gonna count that's
what he needs to get into that 86 for
that's exactly what he had in the semi
because here the dive equally well there
he's got that one under control
Sasha Klein from Germany serves in the
army eight European titles twice he's
been European champion at ten meters but
European Championship two Olympic Games
is some step up arm stand back triple
somersault
or in the pike position the legs just
flipped right over and you don't want to
look at the the scores but they're going
to hear them
this went rather wrong just straightened
up too early and over it went so the
sixes they're gonna hurt the 6065 and
Sasha Cline bit of a smoky for a medal
but maybe not now it was probably better
earlier in the competition he was really
been able to do it on the big stage Nick
McCrory now from the United States 21
years of age from North Carolina forward
four and a half somersault tucked
position three point seven the tariff
here such a hard dive to control at the
end to achieve something like a vertical
position and minimize the splash no
one's really been able to nail this one
high tariffs three seven big splash
count them if you can one two three four
and a half
it wasn't a half he'd go in feet-first
and they just don't do that not
intentionally anyway unfortunately we've
not seen a disaster in this competition
we've had one or two ones go terribly
wrong but not a an incomplete dive which
scores zero was one in the three meter
competition wish that on anyone
victim Adeeb I've reversed three and a
half somersault for the Russian diver
first Olympic Games
excellent work from Viktor the
unmistakable Russian uniform worn by
competitors and supporters alike really
lets you know from that group he was
fourth in the world championships last
year so again he brings good credibility
into the competition he hit that
vertical position very early
now himself to straighten out and
collect an 89.1 he's picked up ten
points on his semi school for the same
dive well done victim and above the last
German to win a medal at ten meters was
yen hempel a silver in the Lanter in 96
but Martin Wolfram has really put
himself in with a chance here in Reverse
three and a half somersault his third
well there we go the first little sign
of pressure and a minor mistake from
Martin liked have had this one back to
have another crack at the entry which
was a little untidy not that it was a
bad position he just didn't to control
the splash as he went beneath he's a
little after pulling the ear down with
you separating the arms dragging it down
and a 7075 five for Martin Tom Daley up
next British national senior champion at
13 years youngest ever European gold
medalist back in 2008 arm stand back
triple somersault three point five is in
fifth place
Nexen a guy from Tom Donnelly wouldn't
matter what he did you get a big role
for him from this crowd but that was
worth cheering
great position on MG he's just an
impression from time to time that he's
not quite square on entry not not the
line of the vertical but square with the
side of the pool and there's a just a
hint of a twist there but unless the
judges spot it like we do on the slo-mo
it's not gonna get too penalized in a 92
75 that's 8 marks better than from the
semi we have three great dives with
Peter Waterfield and a synchro
competition talked and it brought a
massive cheer from the American camp
standby this could be close to 100 he
got ninety four point three five with it
in the semis and this was the four and a
half done beautifully he just scraped
into the semi-final Italy we nearly
didn't have him in this competition and
he is really scoring ninety-nine point
nine that's cruel business liken up for
it in his manner Lin you a far more
composed and restrained back three and a
half somersault even the silver position
he loves this dive he got a hundred and
two for it in the semis but not with
that level of splash though so it might
just hold him back a little great drive
off the platform up and into his word
fantastic position and he's not going to
score 100 this time best individual
performance ever was a bronze at the
2007 World Championships since then he's
really had a chance to dive individually
always in the synchro votes where he's
Donna an Olympic gold almost peerless
through the year ninety one point eight
not in the 90s his little 11 points go
from his semi score and see what all
this means soon enough Q boat reverse
three and a half somersault the leader
approaching the halfway stage this his
third dive three point three the tariff
oh my goodness what a dive how close was
he did a platform we'll get another look
at it to it just increase your heart
rate a little but ninety four oh five in
the semi his tariff for his first three
dives are only three two three five and
thirty three and yet he's going to be at
the top or near and his hard dives are
yet to come
and he's in second spot where those two
tens are that stuff they get ruled out
as the two top scorers along with the
two bottom the tens don't count
now he's just been displaced from the
top following that wonderful ninety nine
point nine from the Daiya here it's
David Boudia who's leading at the moment
he's really responding to this challenge
Chabot and Lynn you a second and third
Tom Daley forth and even Garcia coming
up to fifth Martin Wolfram just dropping
back a little after some very impressive
work
Sasha Klein really starting to fade away
at any bits I think a good thing has
happened here Roger such hot favorites
with chuubo and Lynn UA for someone to
put some pressure on and actually be
leading them at the halfway point could
bring out yet another level from them
out I think we've got a great
competition on our hands now well plenty
of tithers have been in position that to
win the gold in Olympic Games or world
championships they've had to produce a
series of tens we've got a couple in
that previous round but we've not been
absolutely dazzled by a score brilliant
yes but it's still another level where
you feel that maybe they can go Marley
McCormick arm stand back triple
somersault you know marks for how you
get to the arm stand just as long as you
hold it steadily and in good shape so he
likes that split move to the arm stand
fines the water comes in fairly
vertically and gets a nice return the
tows giving us a wave
the directors done well to spot that
hasn't he is a feature to look for in
the apps and the camera just 16 when he
competed in Beijing finished 16th in the
10 meters but progress this time out
Alexander Bondar from Ukraine
back in 11th position for the 18 year
old from Lugansk
this is one of his better dives in 89
won in the semi from Banda is just
failing a little to impress he he's not
gonna be a top five finish it here on
fields on the evidence of his first fall
he was still competing at junior level
last year gold medalist in the European
Junior Championships 10 metre platform
this is with the big boys now though
isn't it
seventy nine point two Banda Devan
Garcia of Mexico two silvers and a
bronze so far for the Mexicans in the
diving pool he's got one of those
Silver's in the 10 metre synchro fifth
he's in the frame if you're interested
in such things a lot of the camera
angles that were showing you are from
cameras that are unmanned if you like
they're on cranes and tracks double
somersault two and a half twists and
this is all human technology yes a
little less than ideal at the at the
entry kicks it out well looks to be
getting through it okay nice form with
the legs and then over she goes and that
was quite a serious mistake on entry
you'll pay for that all very very good
until the last gasp
and at 81 the judge is recognizing that
until you hit the water it was all done
very tidally cosy Guerra
who was Cuba's first ever world
championship medalist back in 2005 in
the synchro with younger a Guerra who
didn't make the cut
arm stand reverse triple somersault now
tucked position three point four the
tariff slightly hesitant arm stand he's
up there now great job and three point
for the tariff
something in the mid to high 80s might
just moving up a spot or two well the
judges do like this nine and a half may
well be his last senior competition
perhaps at 33 still has to get the
motivation and the training but plenty
of life in the old dog yet no that's a
juicy score 96.9 better than anything he
got in the semi final loss is permanent
Sasha Klein from Germany having a
disappointing outing back in 12th back
three-and-a-half somersault eight times
the European champion ah that's better
absolutely ripped that entry they're not
hiding behind a flag now from that
effort from musashi klein they're very
proud of it as he will be and should be
nice and tight in that pipe position
he's turning into a classic example of
that consistency word again as me
because he has shown he's got the real
talent but he just can't maintain that
superb level that the Chinese divers so
far have sustained any of these divers
in the top 12 can match the top one or
two once or twice but it's that
consistency that finds them out across
the six dives playing 72 holes a golf on
a turn of it isn't it see it's that
consistency day-in day-out dive in dive
out for Nick McCrory reverse three and a
half somersault he was back in night
coming into this the fourth dive you may
not be able to improve much here as he
leaps off a platform
see on the house and eights not yet
mentioned that a little bit of nice
trivia about his uncle Gordon Downey
winning a bronze for Great Britain in
the freestyle relay back in a 76 Olympic
Games keeping up the family tradition at
least by appearing in an Olympic final
which is some family tradition onto
Victor mini buy of again from Russia in
sixth place in his first Olympic Games
fourth in the World Championships the
current European silver medalist arm
stand back double somersault two and a
half twist three point six great angle
that yes it but better at the top and at
the bottom unfortunately from any buyers
not so special from the Russian but a
lot of these family connections with the
previous generation having metal you
find this out and Olympics muster FINA
in the artistic gymnastics you picked up
a gold medal on uneven bars you then
find out that her father was a bronze
medalist in greco-roman wrestling so it
often runs in families Russia have
110-meter medals at three of the last
four games but many by have have to go
some Martin Wolfram just slip back a bit
back through and a half somersault for
the twenty year old from Dresden
it's a bit of a crash-landing
I'm sad to say because Wolfram was
having a good competition especially
with his opening couple of dives and
it's just gone missing for him
confidence not there now
short on position coming into the water
and a well that's counting him out a
sixty-four point eight is a disaster in
a final and he may have just the
shoulder come in at the wrong angle Tom
Daly well the public barely have
discovered him four years ago but he was
on the sports radar when he was just ten
and was winning the national under-18
title which is phenomenal now at the
ripe old age of eighteen forward four
and a half somersaults 3.7 the tariff
here this is a biggie for Tom Daley well
the crowd tells you it was very good I'm
not convinced he was completely vertical
but I am convinced by the total lack of
splash and the judge has do like it they
like it a lot and that entry was very
good and a good tariff he's going to
reward him here and he is as well
contributing to a terrific atmosphere
here in the pool and I'm sure that the
other divers despite the waiting in the
support including mr. Beckham the other
divers will be enjoying the the
atmosphere that he's generating and the
scores that is his highest score of the
competition and 98 David Boudia has
shown that he can respond to a challenge
so far
reversed three and a half somersault
three point three a slightly lower
tariff for the student from Purdue
University
oh well yet again we left shaking our
heads to think we nearly didn't see this
man in the final because his diving is
right up there and he's not worried what
Tom Daly might do I have much noise he
gets he's very much focused on his dives
wonderfully tight tuck
oh and he's pulled a 10 that won't count
it's two alone you need three he's
starving like a man who seems to believe
that this might just be his moment da
real conviction ninety point seven five
picked up five points on his semi effort
with the same
now when you quietly and calmly getting
on with his job of racking up these
massively impressive dives forward four
and a half somersault tucked oh and
short all right now he is the little
error that opens the door to the medals
now we've not seen this before he had a
ninety four point three five in the semi
with this one but he's got a problem
right here he was very short bent at the
hips never got too vertical and the
judges could hardly have missed this
this could be really costly it's a big
deduction he's got two dives to try and
make up for what is a 68 for five and
down he tumbles well game on Cubo who's
even more impassive than his countryman
double world champion from the World
Championships last year
back three and a half somersault can be
a 100 point dive for this man and that's
what he got with it in the semi 102
point six is it that good again it's up
there maybe and splash a little bigger
than we saw this morning just
beautifully through the air the judges
can only like that's a very vertical
position
but not as good as the semi and that too
fancy Chinese competitors have got a
real battle on their hands to take what
everyone expected would be theirs
well they did say that this was China's
vulnerable event even though they lost
at three meters and suddenly look at
that David Boudia
from the United States in the lead Kubo
second Tom Daley in the bronze medal
position close a granite there's quite a
gap humble underneath Daley and Lynn UA
has out to fifth well what a shock at
the end of that round it's never over
till it's over
and maybe the pressure is even telling
on the Chinese divers that may well be
the key the excellence of butea the
growing pressure from Daley has put the
Chinese divers under unusual pressure
interesting to see that margin between
third and fourth daily with a little bit
of a buffer 21 points between him and
Guerra and that this is one lively
competition we've got now with two dives
to come from all 12 and the crowd really
know it has really brought this Aquatic
Center right to its feet round five of
six Riley McCormack leads off with a
reverse three and a half somersault
three point three the tariff he's diving
for his own personal standings now
well he kept it in nice and close to the
platform at the finish didn't complement
the start
six out just a little too early so I
overcome the feet past the vertical it's
it's a shame for him it was very solid
until the entry 21 later this month
Rowley mcCormick
still pretty early in his international
career see the analysis starts within
seconds of the completion of the dive
Alexander Banda from Ukraine 12 at the
moment reversed three and a half
somersault
well there was a really unusual kick out
there that the judges might penalize the
legs were on their way to straight he
had a second thought and kicked out
again see if you can notice here there
and again almost a double pump of the
knees Ukraine did only ever won two
Olympic diving medals both of them were
bronze you know Soviet Union had quite a
tradition of course so Ukraine trying to
create their own diving momentum the
judges are just having a little bit of a
struggle with that and they didn't like
it and I think it was the adjustment
that he's made there from four to seven
so someone's missed it and someone and a
couple haven't a little arrow that we
are discussing about
the leg straightening I think he's done
that to save himself and you know he's
been penalized for it even Garcia a
synchro silver medalist sixth-place
reversed three and a half somersault
three point three the tariff and a
little bit behind the breakaway Bunch
back at the peloton almost
well that's a great dive and it really
set itself up with tremendous Heidi got
off the platform you really took off
great her power seventy four point two
five for this one in the semis but he's
through one and a half somersaults
before even passes the platform and the
judges do like it he scored seven and a
half's in the semi he's pulled some
knives here he's produced some big dives
as well during the three competitions so
he's shown as well that he's got
terrific talents at just 18 no no if he
wanted more were tell you he's picked up
15 points and the corresponding dive
from the semi cozy where the senior
player out there tonight at 33 started
to keep going on about his age but in
such a teenage sport it is it's
something he should be proud of after
such a career three and a half
somersault was his fifth dive slap at
the hands as he pulled himself into that
tight tuck position such silence in the
room it's fantastic to hear a little fix
and help tell the story of what's going
on with Serena which is temporarily
extended out to 17,000 seats really has
a good echo effect and reverberates
around the sound which is helping create
this terrific atmosphere Sascha Klein
from Germany pulling herself up a bit
with a much better fourth dive this is
the reverse three and a half somersault
three point three you just know that
there's better stuff enemy a silver
medalist four years ago in the 10-meter
with the synchro and shadow enough in
preliminaries and semi to suggest he
could really make a challenge it's not
quite there it's tough it's supposed to
be tough and it certainly is 5/5
Nick McCrory might just be wondering if
he can benefit from that sudden change
in the top order after Lynne have that
problem he's got a back three and a half
somersault with a 3.3 tariff and not
much room for error if he wants to keep
up his scoring ratio he's the tallest
man in the field at 180 centimeters or
511 if that helps you
so he certainly creates some long lines
through the air but it's about execution
nice job done by McCrory
those long limbs through the air the
arms hands flat to create a necessary
opportunity to pull the unit down after
him below the water and I'm eighty four
one five Victor MIDI by of seventh place
after the fourth round back three and a
half somersault now with three point six
the tariff they're strapping to give
extra support on the wrists they do take
a pounding as they enter the water deep
breaths
to get himself totally composed
excellent job but it was worth the wait
wasn't it got himself set and he adopts
a a really attractive Pike position here
it's not as tight as some in terms of
getting the face down onto the knees but
elegant and scores in the eights from
ninety one point eight well done Victor
Martin Wolfram from Germany next up slip
back after some terrific opening dives
this is his biggest test in terms of
level of competition and finding it a
little tough as it goes on back to a
half somersault two and a half twists
three point six the tariff and after his
dive he's got a deal with the dinner
that is for Tom Daly he's done a nice
job here though and a high scoring die
for him of 88.2 very quickly into the
twists and then try and get the
alignment right after all of that for
the entry you can hear the chairs
building Tom Daly is up next really put
himself in with a great chance in the
timmy to syncro with Peter Waterfield
before the fourth dive went wrong but he
is right in the metal frame now almost a
hundred with his previous dive this is a
three point six tariff back three and a
half somersault piked for the 18-year
old
Oh another good one he's really
channeling the goodwill in the room that
is all for him a lot of smiling faces in
the Aquatic Center as Tom Daly continues
to press for a medal with some stunning
dives and some ripped entries and like
so many British athletes he's just
loving being in London it's been a great
night already for Britain with Mo Farah
winning the 5000 meters just a few
hundred yards away on the track and Tom
Daley is on the charge and he's picked
up another six points on his semi final
dive for the same so watch out David
budaya losing the fact that he's now on
the board and he too has got the scent
of medals he was leading the competition
and after four rounds must be - the
biggest times of his life coming up back
three and a half somersault another good
one from the guy just a little too much
water coming up from the entry but high
tariffs three six he's going to come
under some pressure though not sure if
it was as good as Daly's
and it wasn't he's gonna slot in just
behind him there's nothing in it
so he's for 6605 to dailies for sixty
six point two
[Music]
again the commentator at the venue
appealing to respect the divers turn off
the flashes now perhaps not hot the
build-up to dailies dives well we
mentioned maybe some spectators here
don't understand the instruction then
there'd be some others that don't
understand their camera just how to turn
it off or both yeah Lynn you a now and
it's all threatening to go very wrong
for a 21 year old arm stand back double
somersault two and a half twists with a
three point six tariffs and he needs
something rather special to get back in
the frame that was better
he might have been a little concerned
about this dive that he only scored
seventy five point six within the semies
well he's beaten Chu in the past he's
been a 600 plus scorer set a record at
the national championships this was his
big day I just want to see these scores
from the judges confirmed on the screen
here though I think there's a little bit
of a range here now that's okay eight to
nine that's alright eight and a half's
count is behind both Daly and the diet
cubone out very much the favorite very
much under pressure now forward four and
a half somersault three point seven the
tariff big tariff dive so hard to
control budaya did a spectacular job
with his four and a half not very
sporting that the cheers I suspect and
not because it's brilliant it's a ninety
four point three five it's a great dive
but the cheers are because he's not top
of the leaderboard leaderboard and the
British crowd is going nuts here but Tom
Daly who will lead going into the final
round
I hope this temporary stand is well it
truly made because the roof is
threatening to go off and the
unbelievable beforehand is a possibility
top of the board after round five it is
a hero of Great Britain Tom Daley and
look how close look at that point one
five it's virtually neck-and-neck it's
as close as you can get to a photo well
what a competition this this is it's a
well it's one a way to bring down the
curtain unbelievable
well as we say back home no more than a
struck match between them Allah becomes
just still loving it as we all are - and
just repeat that score so daily is a
head of Buddha and chuubo who are both
tied four six six oh five two four six
six point two oh and then there's a gap
tool in UAE you would think the three
medals barring disaster are with the top
three cool I can't believe those scores
466 points is the leading scorer and
just point to less than point two
separating the top three daughters
unlike in gymnastics if the level share
the medals Riley McCormick now it's the
final round back three and a half
somersault he's in 11th position
excellent excellent diver it's high hard
to focus on the boys starting this sixth
and final round when you know the real
action is in the last three or four but
this was a great dive from the court
well he's reached the final he didn't
manage Valley Beijing when he was just
16 and he'll be pleased at the progress
he's made student from Arizona State in
the United States and a good finish by
the looks of it
well there it is now ninety five point
four not I'm wondering if he's saying
where was that earlier because I really
could have finished a little higher well
done
Alexander Bondar now from Ukraine he's
twelve back two and a half somersault
two and a half twists for the
eighteen-year-old
they all want to finish off with a good
solid performance and a feel good for
what's been a brilliant competition so
far back to an off summer so two and a
half twist then three point six the
tariff
just a little untidy we mentioned an
earlier session one day like to be the
Ukraine sports minister he sets his
sights high but that was all there were
all sorts of problems there in execution
the the knees were bent the ankles went
together sort of lost the thread really
even so it won't be a great scoring dive
for 18-year old he will have his sights
set on Rio
not quite the sign-off that he was
looking for was peering ahead to those
last few dives that await us Roger
Tom Daley has got the least tariff of
the contenders so he's really going to
have to come up with something special
even Garcia great chance of Mexican
Mitchum doing there enjoying himself he
can help himself he missed the final
just by a place no chance to defend
Fairplay to come out tonight and be full
of it for with two and a half somersault
three twists 3.8 at the end of a a bold
program by Evan Garcia of Mexico
[Applause]
a couple of gold medals at the
pan-american games last year in the
10-meter platform and the synchro
10-meter and that silver medal in the
bag for the timid a synchro event so he
and the Mexicans have had a good Olympic
Games in the diving pool
mr. a little pause in the judging
therefore Ivan and the 87 point for his
competition concludes roll down to him
good to see the coach and the diver
there all the hard work they've all put
in together Tom Daley
what he's going through his young mind
mm-hmm Jose Guerra first of all has to
dive back two and a half somersault two
and a half twists three point six he's
in seventh place I said one more time
the 33 year old a wonderful finish from
him he does already have his own slice
of history for his nation with a second
placing at the o-5 world's in Montreal
Cuba's first world championship medal
and he continues to compete at the top a
wonderful final diver from where'er
oldest diver in the competition
well what a great sign off that is
ninety seven point two well I'm truly
eclipsing anything he scored in the
semies respect is the word I think
respect and we're getting close
Sasha Klein back to a half somersault
two and a half twists tenth position for
the twenty six-year-old already has an
Olympic silver from Beijing in the
synchro back to half somersault two and
a half twist then three point six to
conclude we're seeing some divers finish
off their competition very nicely
Sasha Klein gesture a little erratic on
the finals night needed six times like
that got a different outcome but well
done to hold it together for his final
dive knowing was out of contention
just the scoring from the judges seems
to have slowed down Roger I couldn't
even guess why that might be but maybe
the tension getting to them to knowing
what's sitting in front of them
trying to separate three divers with
point one favor between them I want to
make sure they get it right what's right
as you can do in what is a subjective
sport after all now Mick McCrory from
the United States 21 year old sixth in
the world championships last year know
going into this final dive oh and
another excellent final dive from their
finalists McCrory well done
maybe the whole occasion the drama the
crowd the atmosphere is getting to all
of them willing them to put on a real
show special night he did score a 90 for
this dive in the semis
and a ninety seven point two it speaks
to their endurance and concentration
that they can pull out another big dive
to finish it off
Victor Mille buyers 5th place back to a
half somersault two and a half twist out
of the middle frame but he's had a good
competition in his first olympic games
the 21 year old certainly not short of
high tariffs dives
and yet another top dive many buyers
last three days are all 3.6
well he's second is a 3.7 sets the bar
high and he has cleared it easily here
in style sense of anticipation around
this pool as we get nearer to these
crucial final dives and a ninety one
point eight for Victor brings a smile
and as he finishes his Olympic campaign
I just hope the crowd has some
appreciation of what a difference the
degree of difficulty is going to make
for Tom Daley
he's jumping into the water with a 3.3
and the others three point six Martin
bull from eighth place going into this
final dive which is a forward
four-and-a-half somersault with a three
point seven tariff in his first Olympic
Games
but that shoulder issue it's not even
paddling with that arm I hope he hasn't
done something serious here and I think
he has he looks even he is struggling he
is in trouble and this is most
concerning his hope he hasn't suffered a
little dislocation there he's managed to
get himself up onto the pool edge that
looks like a dislocation to me what a
way to end that's not the case but he's
in trouble
[Applause]
I'll just try and keep that stabilized
but I don't like the way that hanging
yes a little bone pointing the way it
should not so that is the danger of this
sport now well now we come down to what
it's all about if we didn't have enough
drama right we've got an injury and now
a nation hoping that Tom Daley can
produce something special the biggest
two seconds of his life ahead of him Tom
Daley leading in gold medal position his
final dive just at three point three
tariffs on a reverse three and a half
somersault but he is diving for gold
must extract maximum value from this one
silence oh it's good oh it's better than
good they're on their feet they love him
he knows it's good I think he's
relishing in the reception too he's laid
down the challenge you beat me if you're
good enough at last we see that Daley
smile
Oh cometh the Romans baby cometh Tom
daily 90.7 5 he's just beating his score
from the semi when he also had some
nines in there this was beautiful tight
tuck look at the finish here
absolutely vertical by the time he hits
the water the splash is barely there and
he is richly rewarded but hold on folks
because there's some tough dives with
bigger difficulty coming he knows so
that he has put on the big show and he
will be delighted at that and the young
lad comes through for the first time
rather than the more introverted figure
in competition now David Boudia has
responded to every challenge amateur
American diver now this he will believe
is his moment three point six his Terry
forgot I've emphasized that back two and
a half somersault two and a half twist
oh it's good - and Tom Daley's got to be
concerned about that it only needs to
beat him by one point and he's out of
the gold medal position and budaya waits
and hopes what a competition he's put
together 24 hours ago he was nearly out
of it he is relaxed he said he relaxed
and he's been enjoying it and this is
nail-biting
oh he's there oh he's more than there a
hundred and 2.6
he has stormed to top position oh what a
moment for this man a career highlights
it's not over yet there's still the
favorite to go
not to mention Lin you a only one diver
in the last three games from China was
missed out on a 10 meter medal so he
will be feeling in this rare opportunity
to compete individually that he has
missed the boat back to an a half
somersault till the half twists it's not
good enough there was a separation of
the ankles the entry wasn't quite right
and it's not quite good enough I would
feel leave it to the judges but
uncharacteristically the ankles not
locked together the splash too big the
chance for medals they're not used to it
general in
the Women's Champion we saw down there
on the bench they're all out there
supporting they came here for the clean
sweep of eight golds they're looking for
seven they may have to settle for six
Tom Daley knows he's got a middle it's
just what color
so does budaya there's just one man to
come could see the pressure just lifted
off Tom Daley that read I've that
opening read I've world
Kubo the pre-race favorite as it were
back two and a half somersault two and a
half twist the last dive of these
Olympic Games what a competition well it
was good but is it a hundred dive but
Dyer might be the man she roll off that
2009 World Championships to Tom Daley
right in the final dive he knows what
it's like just not quite perfect with
the entry there was a bigger splash than
we're used to seeing from this man
through the air beautiful the finish not
the very best impression he could leave
he wants to see what this is and he's
forced his way between birdurer and
Daley so but Dyer is your champion David
Boudia of American foes in the great
tradition the great days are back for
American diving and the Chinese have to
settle for second place with Cuba the
favorite Tom Daley gets the bronze a
brilliant dramatic staggering
competition and David Boudia
comes out of the pool on top of the
world well it's a competition that
anyone who's seen it here or at home
will remember for many a day we've had
all sorts of drama here but to bow is
crushed
coming up short coming up short 29.5 and
a nine and that is not enough for Tom
Daley knows how tough it is to get a
medal in this 10 metre platform diving
event and he is the first Britney since
Brian Phelps back in 1960 52 years ago
and David booty bringing the good times
back to diving in the United States he
has to settle Steve your thoughts well
I'm just staggered at birdies
competition you know last night and he
was inconsistent he was all over the
place he fell into the brook into the
semi-final then he impressed us good
diet by qualifying in third best
position and now he's won it and that
top score of 100 and 2.6 for his final
dive just blew them away and Kubo five
dives in the 90 and a 100 not good
enough that tells you how good bird I
was and Tom Daley has thrilled this
British crown I'm just just feel
privileged to be sitting here to have
seen it and to have enjoyed it and to
watch these men under pressure perform
so exciting a new experience this for a
massive crowd not used to big crowds in
diving events in this country and they
have seen something quite unforgettable
and never presume it's over to bow a
tearful figure he has had his success
daily budaya
23 year old from Abilene in Texas will
feel that he has worked for this and
he's worked for this over three sessions
general in their sharing the tears they
went together and lose together the
Chinese team but the Stars and Stripes
are getting ready to be unfurled and
hang high a great respect from all the
divers they know this has been a great
competition
well they were expected to and lean to
take the top two places but there's only
room for one of them on the podium and
it'll be a silver medal and Padilla's
come from tenth four years ago to first
in London it's been a long journey and a
very successful and happy one for him
now he's dominated at home in the state
16 national titles he's won the United
States this is their one hundred and
twenty ninth diving medal they used to
dominate before the Chinese entered the
games and then stole their show but now
this will mean so much to them to be
back on top of the platform and we know
about David that you know originally
with this discipline he was scared of
heights he had some work done with the
sports psychologist he now describes it
as a walk in the park well wherever he
walks now he's going to be recognized as
a gold medalist and someone who won a
most extraordinary competition here and
by less than two points from Chabot and
Tom Daley sin behind a true bow but well
clear a victim in a buy of an absolutely
worthy medalist oh my goodness what a
competition Roger Lynn you a will be
distraught their expectations and the
pressure on them is so high and for many
of these divers their time will come
again just teenagers half the field
remember it was their first Olympic
Games and the great look Greg Louganis
being introduced to the crowd they the
real Idol of American diving an iconic
figure and he more than anyone will be
delighted to see an American ride at the
top of diving's blue-ribbon event such a
buzz in this place as well you don't
have to know a lot about diving to know
you've been at something special now the
gayness a winner of this event
in Los Angeles and soul class de Bercy
of Italy one at three in a row the
British team all in there they know what
pressure tom has been under of course
his father died and he'd been such a
support and a presence to him he'd be
bullied at school all his life seems to
be played out in a public spotlight Bert
and let's go back again to that first
dive where he was distracted by camera
flashes in the crowd he was given a
seventy five point six wisely he and his
coach appealed FINA took a sympathetic
view here II dived and went from seventy
five point six to ninety one point two
and that proved absolutely crucial took
some nerve to to do that to have the the
professionalism to say that it's it's
all history now actually when you look
at the margin between third and fourth
it was more than that the fifteen points
so in the end there won't be any
protests from those beneath him because
he was so clearly in third place and
that's of some comfort I think to anyone
who might have wanted the question
whether he should have been allowed to
read I've because the margin made sure
it wasn't an issue in the end but it did
have a massive effect on his confidence
absolutely yeah
put him in contention and ask questions
of the dire and shubo he's getting all
the coverage here because of his special
place in the British consciousness he
and Jessica Ennis were the two poster
boy and girl he will feel as though he's
got his gold really by being on that
podium as David Boudia though we'll take
all the plaudits a to bow with an
Olympic silver medal almost feeling like
they forgot man in all these
celebrations yes
I think the weight of expectation was
well and truly on his shoulders and he
and he simply didn't dive quite as well
as he did in the semies it's about
delivering when the medals are on offer
those earlier scores of course don't
carry forward to the final and the dyer
saves his best when it matters
bronze on a silver his Hall from these
Olympic Games the world championships
are in Barcelona for swimming next year
when these divers will recon grenades
they will have to be righter their very
best to match a show like this but it's
that Olympic title that is the big one
that's what makes you a diving immortal
so we won't be far away from a medal
presentation and nearly everyone is
staying for it and so are we
I've been impressed with the way crowds
have stayed you know the extra extra
minutes - even if there's been no
British competitor on that on the day I
did a lot of sessions of gymnastics and
observed that that was the case every
time and that makes a difference to the
athletes Roger well the pool has to be
said was hopelessly one-sided in its
support but within that there was still
a full emotional range throughout the
three sessions of the diving for those
divers who really performed brilliantly
and those who may be disappointed once
got to say that those are slightly
disappointing marks for the top guys in
the last round or two were fairly
enthusiastically received by the crowd
but in general the atmosphere has been
very special and it's another successful
competition in these London 2012 games
walking to the Aquatic Centre across the
Olympic Park past the stadium this
evening the atmosphere around it was a
glorious summer's evening and you can't
always say that in Stratford even in
August and the atmosphere was great
every different country was mixing there
were loads of Dutch fans going to see
the hockey everybody's streaming there
with their colours and the atmosphere
was absolutely special as it has been
about two weeks and for everybody lucky
enough to get a ticket in here tonight
then this competition and the drama and
the excitement of it all and a happy
enough ending for the crowd has really
topped it off and that's special yeah
and when you enjoy an evening like
tonight outside especially as you say
Roger you realize you just blow away all
your cynicism about the Olympics
whatever that those cynicism might be
and rejoice in the human spirit that's
it and the goodness that's out there and
the happiness that it generates on a
night like tonight when it's just great
fun to be around Olympic Park this is
what it's all about and when you bring
an olympics to a city you hope to
capture that and it's it's been done
here that's for sure and and a big
contributor to that every time when it
works is the volunteers the quality and
the attitude of the volunteer zone I've
been really impressed and I've been
lucky enough to attend six Olympics and
no one's done it better than here in
terms of making everyone from overseas
and locally feel so welcome well that's
terrific to hear I've been around a
quite a few different events during the
last two weeks not all have been gold
medal events but of weightlifting and
rowing a real range of sports handball
even an arena has been packed out and
the board is turning up watching sports
they know nothing about and people they
know nothing about and paying quite a
bit of money for it and just being
delighted to be there and be a part of
it if you're just joining us we're
awaiting the middle presentation for the
10-meter platform a quite sensational
evening of competition
tinged with a little bit of drama and
sadness for the injury to Martin Wolfram
whether what we suspect was a shoulder
dislocation on his last dive the word
about the Chinese divers as well because
the standards they've set and the way
that they have hauled the sport for
words with their exemplary performances
in no way is it decrying their efforts
because people are almost celebrating
are they being beaten it's a it is a
backhanded compliment in that way but
they've set their standards so high but
it does prove that nobody wins all the
time every time and what it proves to is
it in the last round pressure puts a
microscope bar on your ability to cope
with what's happening and sometimes you
can just expose a weakness that maybe
you can deal with in years to come when
once you've had the experience of
dealing with it I think that's what
David padorin particularly did because
he was following Tom Daley the crowd
were really up he was the Chinese were
next and he always seemed to respond and
kept that pressure on the two Chinese
divers and to some extent to different
extents they did crack now we're ready
for that victory ceremony which will be
raucously supported from all quarters
they are really going to enjoy the next
10 minutes
we've got two very happy men and a
slightly disconsolate chuubo you really
expected to win his country expected him
to but any competitor should be proud
and pleased to receive silver he feeling
Burton golden bronze nobody gonna enjoy
this we use our Ching
and he was vice president of the Beijing
Games Organising Committee for six years
he might just have been expecting to
present a gold medal to one of his
countrymen
president of FINA but the Julio says our
malli own a Ruiz from Uruguay presents
the flowers Tom Bailey cough and get up
on that platform quick enough the first
Tim meter medal for Great Britain since
1960 52 years just listen to this
every mum throughout the land to be
saying our blessing weren't they
yeah that that's a smile that you'll see
across newspapers across the world
you've got to be a hard man not to
really have your heart go out to him
what he's been through and he'll be
thinking of his late father in this
moment I'm absolutely sure gonna be one
of the happiest prawns medals of the
games I think so and you could see the
digestion to the crowd that he's saying
yes you know thank you for your support
this is for you too for to bow more
dazzling skills but just for once the
world champion has to miss out
[Applause]
now let's see the unpredictability of
sport the hottest of favourites coming
in but he didn't reckon perhaps on the
performance David Boudia the jerseys
moment which is standing evenings
competition and a bit of a smile at last
from the 19 year old and the gracious
bow from all the Chinese divers as ever
but it takes a a great diver to win a
great competition and the gold medallist
is from the United States the good days
are rolling again for diving in the
state David Boudia wins the gold
to think that less than two tenths of a
point separated that the top three
divers coming into that last round he
held his nerve he pulled out a one
hundred and two point six to win it and
to win it by a couple of points well
done David and his experience having
been to a games before maybe that helped
him and we'll say it one final time he
nearly didn't even make the semi-final
[Music]
you can hardly believe it I just want to
shoot you the ranking of where he was
after each series of dives equal first
after the first equal third first first
equals second and first he was the most
consistent man who talked about quality
and consistency at the start David
Boudia delivered it and he's being
delivered a gold medal nobody's coming
nobody's come to the early bus have a
note to bow was only in front after the
second series of dives equal fourth
after the first thin first second second
second second never quite cracked it
they were posed for the photographs now
and enjoy the moment
I think Tom Daley's going to do his own
victory lap in front of all these
supporters now they can take their
photographs and use their flash guns as
much as they want now he's going up into
the crowd there
[Applause]
it's gonna make the most of this moment
tried to steal the show David Boudia
doesn't mind he's got the gold they're
really supposed to march around together
so that the photographers can get the
shot of the three of them together but
David Boudia has been thrown the Stars
and Stripes that's all good we're nearly
at the end of the journey at me Rajan is
a sense of almost melancholy and sadness
that the this great party is coming to
an end they're going to celebrate as
well there is a great camaraderie
one senses between the divers
[Applause]
great staff just enjoy these scenes
moments to cherish
[Applause]
I hope to bow also realizes the party
played what a contribution he's made to
10-meter platform diving and just
throwing here - Roger that you don't get
a wonderful competition like this unless
you've got three or four guys competing
at the very top providing you with real
drama it's not really as exciting if one
man races away with it to have to bow
and Tom Daley they're pushing the dire
all the way and to get the surprise
result this is one of the great
competitions you'll see in diving you
need more than one man to be standing up
and giving you a story so a great
competition for the United States who
got off to a good start with David
Boudia winning bronze in that 10 metre
synchro and it gave the rest of the
American diving team a bit of momentum
he started in boy has he finished it six
out of eight then for Chinese diving
three meters and 10 meters for men let
it down and when he said your standard
so high he couldn't understand
disappointment with silver but Tom Daley
pretty happy with bronze to say the
least
well the blow torch of Olympic
competition shows the strengths and
frailties of the athlete I saw all of
that tonight and we would come away with
a wonderful feeling about the health of
the sport the competitors who give us
the pleasure from it
just delighted to have been here States
got a silver in the women's three metre
synchro and a couple of bronze in the
men's three metre synchro as well and
it's and you may comes to the Brian
getting that women's silver so a gold
silver and two bronze for the United
States well this party's going to carry
on for quite some time Steve thank you
very much for your contribution as we
confirm the final result and some
dazzling statistical work if I might say
so
for an artistic sport you can certainly
crunch a few numbers well the statistics
are also important out there when you're
looking at degrees of difficulty and in
execution the number that really matters
is the mess on top at the end and David
Boudia
particularly with that 102 last dive to
produce that under pressure reminiscent
in some ways of the finishing in Beijing
four years ago remember some of those
names down the bottom end just teenagers
in their first Olympic Games they will
be competing that the standard is set so
high now the end of a couple of
astonishing weeks of great competition
in this Aquatic Center 17,000 capacity
and boy they all had their money's worth
a great competition here in the 10-meter
platform diving and I think there's a
bit of a party going to be happening in
the United States camp and also in the
British camp if you're scared of heights
look away now as we take you to the edge
of the platform and consider what the
competitors head six times over before
you worry that is an automatic suspended
camera there's not some poor chap
holding that one but again just to recap
here it was an American gold a Chinese
silver and a very British bronze here in
the 10-meter platform
maybe just to enjoy these final few
memories from this great night of
competition and certainly hope you've
enjoyed it
[Music]
how to remember at all I'm sure you'll
remember some of it and especially the
end and the joy of victory for birdie
and bronze for daily a great night off
the platform was the game just our
pleasure to bring it to you